<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Uncertainty on Dylan Ler</title><link>https://dylanler.github.io/tags/uncertainty/</link><description>Recent content in Uncertainty on Dylan Ler</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 10:00:00 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://dylanler.github.io/tags/uncertainty/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>When Do LLMs Know They Do Not Know? Metacognition and Calibrated Uncertainty</title><link>https://dylanler.github.io/posts/metacognition-when-llms-know-they-dont-know/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 10:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://dylanler.github.io/posts/metacognition-when-llms-know-they-dont-know/</guid><description>&amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know&amp;rdquo; might be the most important thing an AI can learn to say.
This experiment tests whether LLMs have calibrated uncertainty—knowing when they&amp;rsquo;re likely to be wrong and expressing appropriate confidence levels. The results reveal systematic patterns of overconfidence and appropriate humility.
The Experiment We presented 250 questions across 5 categories:
Factual recall: Known facts with clear answers Reasoning puzzles: Logic problems with determinable solutions Ambiguous questions: Multiple valid interpretations Knowledge boundaries: Questions near training cutoff Impossible questions: No correct answer exists For each question, models provided:</description></item><item><title>Wisdom of Crowds: What LLM Disagreement Reveals About AI Uncertainty</title><link>https://dylanler.github.io/posts/wisdom-of-crowds-ensemble-disagreement/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 10:15:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>https://dylanler.github.io/posts/wisdom-of-crowds-ensemble-disagreement/</guid><description>When multiple AI models disagree, what does that tell us?
The &amp;ldquo;wisdom of crowds&amp;rdquo; phenomenon shows that aggregating independent judgments often outperforms individual experts. But for AI systems, ensemble disagreement might reveal something deeper: the structure of uncertainty itself.
The Hypothesis When multiple LLMs disagree on a question, the pattern of disagreement reveals the epistemological nature of the problem:
High agreement → Robust, well-established knowledge Systematic disagreement → Genuine ambiguity or value-laden territory Random disagreement → Knowledge gaps or reasoning failures Experiment Design We queried 4 models (Claude Opus 4.</description></item></channel></rss>