<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Dylan Ler</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Dylan Ler</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.133.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Nov 2018 22:40:56 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Self Help Books</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/self-help-books/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Nov 2018 22:40:56 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/self-help-books/</guid>
      <description>Thoughts about self-help books 📚 People often ask me to recommend a self-help book that might help them achieve something be it losing weight, investing, building careers and etc.
Till date I always have the same reply, &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t read self-help books&amp;rdquo;.
I mean I&amp;rsquo;m sure self-help books can be useful if you can apply what the author is asking you to do seamlessly into your life. However I find that to be easier said than done.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;s Hard to Notice the Little Things</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-little-things/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/the-little-things/</guid>
      <description>For the past few weeks, I&amp;rsquo;ve been listening to startup founders about how they scaled their companies while preserving their core values at the same time. As such, I will be summarizing some of the recurring elements that stood out to me.
One thing that really surprised me is that really large companies are not run as efficiently as you think. A lot of times, bureaucracy gets piled up that causes employees to lose the initial spark they had when they joined the company.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From a Family to a Tribe</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/family-to-tribe/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/family-to-tribe/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;CEO/founders should interview every candidate until the company is at least 500 employees.&amp;rdquo; — Keith Rabois
Good news. Your startup has gained some kind of traction and has finally achieved some sort of product-market-fit. You, the founder, are assuming the roles of all the C-suite executives. You are making sales calls, you are having meetings every other day, you are managing the back-end server of your startup and you have no sleep.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boring Work Pays Off</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/boring-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/boring-work/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;If you think of all the things that make for good TV, do none of them. Focus on the things that make for boring TV — sitting and coding, talking with customers, making sales calls.&amp;rdquo; — Sam Altman
The family stage of startups as defined by Reid Hoffman is the stage where a startup has assembled its founding team and is ready to take on the world with their minimum viable product.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
